Guide to the Jack London Papers, 1897 - 1916
Department of Special Collections
Jack London Papers,
1897 - 1916
Special Collections M0077
London, Jack, 1876 - 1916
1.25 linear ft.
Stanford University. Libraries. Dept. of Special Collections and University Archives.
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
None.
Provenance
Purchase, 1940; gift of Felton Elkins, 1942; gift of Christian deGuigne, 1964; and gift of Arnold G. Applegarth, 1986.
Biography
Jack London was born in San Francisco January 12, 1876. He led an adventurous life, only beginning his career as an author in the 1890s. He wrote short stories, serials, essays, articles, verse and novels. He died November 22, 1916 in Sonoma County, CA.
Scope and Content
Chiefly letters by London to Mabel and Edward M. Applegarth; to his English literary agent, James B. Pinker; and to his daughters. Also includes manuscripts of two longer works and nine poems by London, five poems by Edward Applegarth, several letters and postcards by Charmian London, and photographs. There is an ink wash painting by Maynard Dixon done for London's SON OF WOLF.
Access terms
Applegarth, Edward M.; Applegarth, J.H.; Applegarth, Mabel.; Dixon, Maynard.; London, Charmian.; London, Jack, 1876-1916.; Pinker, James B.; Porter, W.S.; American literature--20th century.; Authors, American--20th century.; London, Jack, 1876-1916--Photographs.; Photoprints.
Container List
- Series I: Correspondence, 1897 - 1940, and n.d.
  - London, Jack to Edward Applegarth (Box 1, Folder 1)
    - 1897, June 22,2 pp.
    - 1898, Sept. 13,15pp.
    - 1898, Nov. 14,2pp.
    - 1898, Dec. 6,2pp.
    - 1898, Dec. 31,4pp.
    - 1899, Mar. 15,1pg.
    - 1901, Mar. 19,1pg.
  - London, Jack to J.H. "Bert" Applegarth (Box 1, Folder 2)
    - 1906, Nov.28,4pp., with envelope
  - London, Jack to Mabel Applegarth (Box 1, Folder 3)
    - 1897, Aug. 8,2pp.
    - 1898, Nov. 16,1pg.
    - 1905, Mar. 2,1pg.
    - 1905, Sept. 12,6pp.
  - London, Jack to Mabel Applegarth, with note n.d. (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - London, Jack to daughter, Bess London (Box 1, Folder 5)
    - 1906 - 190816 postcards
  - London, Jack, to daughter, Bess London (Box 1, Folder 6)
    - 1908, Oct. 28,2pp.
  - London, Jack, to daughter, Joan London (Box 1, Folder 7)
    - 1906 - 19099 postcards
  - Pressbook, "Letters of Jack London to James B. Pinker," volume 1, J. London to J. Pinker, 85 letters. Also includes letters to Mr. Pinker referring to Jack London. 1902, Oct 28 - 1906, Nov. 19 (Box 1, Folder 8)
    - Shurmer Sibthorp to Pinker, 1904, Jan. 26
    - R.S. Garnett to Pinker, 1906, Mar. 13
    - A. Hutchinson to Pinker, 1906, Dec. 18
    - J. Pinker to J. London, 1904, Sept. 27
    - Stuart Reid to J. London, 1906, May 4
  - Pressbook, "Letters of Jack London to James B. Pinker," volume 2, J. London to J. Pinker, 54 letters. Also includes letters to Mr. Pinker referring to Jack London and/or his estate. 1907, Jan. 25 - 1913, Dec. 5 (Box 1, Folder 9)
    - George D. Brett, President of Macmillian Co., to Pinker, 1907, Oct. 16
    - Ninetta Eames, attorney in fact for Jack London, to Pinker
      - 1907, Nov. 30
      - 1908, Jan. 2
      - 1908, Feb. 27
      - 1908, Apr. 3
      - 1908, Apr. 21
    - R. Sommerville, Manager of Cassell's General Press, to Pinker, 1908, Oct. 28
    - Hodder & Stroughton to Pinker, 1909, Oct. 19
    - T. Werner Laurie LTD. to Pinker. Includes a copy of an authorization by Jack London for Mr. Hughes Hessie. 1913, Aug. 30
    - A. Byrne, Secretary of and in behalf of Jack London, to Pinker, 1916, July 24
    - Eliza Shepard, Executor of Jack London's estate, to Pinker, 1921, May 25
    - Eliza London Shepard to Pinker, 1927, Dec. 20
    - James B. Pinker & Sons to Mrs. Jack London, (written on the lower part of this letter is a letter from Mrs. Eloiza London Shepard to Pinker, n.d.) 1929, June 26
    - Jack London's letter to Pinker includes a copy of his article defending himself against a charge of plagiarism by a Mr. Frank Harris, 1909, July 1
  - London, Jack to "Comrades [Socialist Party]," typed copy signed, 1 pg. 1916, Mar. 7 (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - London, Jack to unknown, third and final page of a letter with London's signature, 3 inner pages of a letter. (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - London, Jack, 2 facsimilie letters 1900, Jan. 31 (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - London, Charmian, outgoing correspondence (Box 1, Folder 13)
    - To Dr. W.S. Porter, envelope, postmarked 1914, Mar. 2
    - To Dr. W.S. Porter, postcard 1919, Dec. 20
    - To Jeanette M. Hitchcock, postcard, 1940, Oct. 30
    - To Jeanette M. Hitchcock, postcard, 1940, Nov. 4
    - To Dr. Porter, note, in an envelope labeled "Jack London's "The Son and the Wolf", frontispiece by Maynard Dixon. n.d.
    - To an unknown, second and final page of a note (was enclosed in "The Book of Jack London" by Charmian London)
  - Unknown to Charmian London, typed letter, 6 pp. 1947, Apr. 29 (Box 1, Folder 14)
- Series II: Literary Manuscripts, 1900 - 1901, n.d.
  - London, Jack; Nine Poems 1901 (Box 2, Folder 1)
    - "The Lover's Liturgy," 3 pp.
    - "At Daybreak," 1pg.
    - "The Worker's Tribute to the Tramp (Villanelle)," 1pg.
    - "Gold," 2 pp.
    - "The Socialist's Dream," 2pp.
    - "Je Ris en Espair," 1pg.
    - "Hors de Saison," 2pp.
    - "Ballad of the False Lover," 1 pp.
    - "The Return of Ulysses--A Modern Version," 7 pp.
  - London, Jack; manuscript, "The Jacket," (later called "The Star Roamer,") (Box 2, Folder 2)
    - pp. 1-49
  - London, Jack; manuscript, "The Jacket," (later called "The Star Roamer,") (Box 2, Folder 3)
    - pp. 50-96
  - London, Jack; manuscript, "The Jacket," (later called "The Star Roamer,") (Box 2, Folder 4)
    - pp. 97-146
  - London, Jack; manuscript, "The Jacket," (later called "The Star Roamer,") (Box 2, Folder 5)
    - pp. 147-193
  - London, Jack; manuscript, "The Jacket," (later called "The Star Roamer,") (Box 2, Folder 6)
    - pp. 194-249
  - (Box 2, Folder 7)
    - London, Jack; manuscript, "The Little Lady of the Big House," titlepage - p.45
  - (Box 2, Folder 8)
    - London, Jack; manuscript, "The Little Lady of the Big House," pp. 46-91
  - (Box 2, Folder 9)
    - London, Jack; manuscript, "The Little Lady of the Big House," pp. 92-138
  - (Box 2, Folder 10)
    - London, Jack; manuscript, "The Little Lady of the Big House," pp. 139-184
  - (Box 2, Folder 11)
    - London, Jack; manuscript, "The Little Lady of the Big House," pp. 185-229
  - (Box 2, Folder 12)
    - London, Jack; manuscript, "The Little Lady of the Big House," pp. 230-266
  - London, Jack, 5 carbon typescripts of poems (Box 2, Folder 13)
    - "Cupid's Deal," 2pp.
    - "A Heart," 4pp.
    - "My Little Palmist," 3pp.
    - "Triolets," 2pp.
    - "Triolets," 1pg. partial copy
  - Applegarth, Edward M., 5 poems (Box 2, Folder 14)
    - "This is the Day of Days--The Day of Death--," (copy as sent to Mr. Clures), 1pg.
    - "The White Silence of the North," 1pg.
    - "Living," 1 pg.
    - "Parting," 1 pg.
    - "Lilith," 1 pg.
- Series III: Ephemera, 1908 - 1916
  - London's family ephemera (Box 2, Folder 15)
    - Joan London's list of class grades, 1908 June 5
    - Jack London, cancelled check to Consolidated Soda Water Works, Co. for $1.20, 1916, Jan. 8
    - Unused picture postcard "Peche Au Harpon, Tahiti"
- Series IV: Photographs, 1898, 1907, and n.d.
  - Photographs of Jack London (Box 2, Folder 16)
    - Jack London (2)
    - Jack London, Aunt Louise Applegarth, John Dewey, "Pop Bert" Applegarth, "Chinese Cook",and Mabel Applegarth in Yosemite Park, 1898 (with negative)
    - Jack London, Bess Madden, Mabel Applegarth, and dogs: Yosemite and Pug, (negative of print also included)
    - Jack London and second wife Charmian Kittredge London, taken in 1907 in Honolulu during the sojourn of the "Snark," on her maiden voyage.
    - London
- Series V: Painting, ca. 1899
  - Maynard Dixon's charcoal with ink wash painting for the frontispiece of London's "The Son of Wolf" (Box 1)